PACT

by Winston P. Sanders (Poul Anderson)

As Commiczar of Brimstone Production & Stenches, Ashmadai rated a private office— which was essential to his daring, forbidden plan to summon up a human . . .

HOW ASHMADAI CAME TO DECIDE, in the teeth of all modern skeptical science, that certain ancient legends were sober truth; and how he then quested for the book he must have, and finally succeeded: would make a story in itself. But not our story.

A longer time passed before he had assembled the needful ingredients, not to mention the needful courage. At last, on a certain hour, he rang for his secretary. She came hopping in and bellowed, "Yes, sir?”

“I have an urgent job on hand,” said Ashmadai. “I am not to be disturbed by anything, for any reason whatsoever, until I tell you otherwise. Is that clear?” He was pleased, and a little surprised, by his own calm tones.

"Yes, sir,” nodded the secretary. "No inter’crence. Unless His In’ernal ‘A’esty calls.” Her fangs, though impressive, hampered her diction; so of course her one desire was to go on the stage.

"Indeed,” said Ashmadai sarcastically. “Or unless Armageddon is declared. Now get out there and guard my privacy!”

The secretary groveled and hopped away again. Ashmadai glided from behind the obsidian desk to the door, which he locked. Returning to the windows, he made sure that no one was flying past or peering in. Not that it had been likely. As Commiczar of Brimstone Production & Stenches, Ashmadai rated an office in the third-from-lowest subbasement of the Hotiron Building. Only the most exclusive traffic was allowod in these lanes. All that he saw was the usual great hollow vista, touched here and there with flamelight. Perceptions sharpened by excitement, he slanted his ears forward as a loud and clear shriek of agony rose above the general hubbub. "A Flat,” he nodded, and gestured the windows to close their lids.

Allowing himself no time to become frightened, he opened a drawer. The moldering old folio, bound in dragon skin, came out first. He laid it on his desk and checked the ritual once more while he assembled paraphernalia. And then to work.

The first item of procedure was painful but not unendurable, reciting the Lord’s Prayer sideways. What followed was so ghastly that Ashmadai, having completed it, went through everything else in a mercifully numb state. But by the time he had chalked the Mobius strip on the three-dimensional floor, he was recovering, and he cried the final “Venite, venite, venite!” on an almost arrogant note.

There was a brilliant, soundless flash. When Ashmadai could see again, a man stood within the diagram,

Ashmadai crouched back. He had expected the formula to work. But the actuality— He found himself shaking, lit a cigar and puffed hard. Only then could he face the one he had summoned.

Even by Ashmadai’s standards (he considered himself a handsome devil) the man was not acutely nauseating. He was about the same size, also bifurcate though lacking horns, wings, or tail. He was in his shabby shirtsleeves, but gave no impression of poverty. An aged specimen, Ashmadai saw, lean and bald, with skin like crumpled parchment. So what made him so terrible? After a moment, Ashmadai decided it was the eyes. Behind the tbick- lensed glasses, they crackled with a more than common intensity. And behind them was a soul. . . . Ashmadai fought down the ancient envious hunger.

The man scuttled about for a while, trying to get out of the Mobius strip but failing. (The book warned of unspeakable consequences if a human, summoned, should escape before a covenant had been arrived at.) But presently the being calmed himself. He stood with folded arms and stiff lips, peering into the flickerlit murk around him.

When he saw Ashmadai, he nodded, “I hadn’t believed that nonsense,” he said, with an oldster’s parched chuckle. "But I am not dreaming. There is far too much detail; and, also, once I have realized that I am dreaming, I always awaken. Therefore, common sense must give way to fact. Are they really saucer shaped?”

Ashmadai gaped. “What?”

“Your spaceships.”

“Spaceships?” Ashmadai thumbed mentally through all the human languages of all the ages, searching for the concept. “Oh, I see. I don’t have a spaceship.”

“No? Well, what do you use, then? A, all, hyperspatial tube, I believe the current fantasy term is?” The man gagged. “I’m well aware that that is a mathematically meaningless noise. But I take it you had some method of transporting me to your planet.”

“Planet? I haven’t any planet,” said Ashmadai, more bewildered than ever. “I mean, well, after all, I date back to the Beginning, when there weren’t any planets to be born under. Not even a Zodiac.”

“Just a minute!” bristled the man, as nearly as a hairless person can bristle. “I may belong to a species technologically beliind your own, but you needn’t insult my intelligence. We have established that the universe was created at least five billion years ago.”

“8,753,271,413 ” nodded Ashmadai slowly.

“What? Well, then, do you mean to stand there and make the preposterous claim that you are of erfual age? Why, the mnemonic problem alone invalidates the assertion--”

“Whoa!” exclaimed Ashmadai. "Wait a second, please, milord . . . citizen . . . comrade . . . whatever they’re calling themselves on Earth nowadays—”

“Plain ‘mister’ will do. Mr. Hobart Clipp. No Ph.D. in his right mind uses “Doctor before his name. Not unless he wants every idiot introduced to him to embark on a list of symptoms."

"Mr. Clipp.” Ashmadai found bis usual suavity coming back. “Very pleased to meet you. My name is Ashmadai. My public name, that is. You would hardly expect me to tender my real one, any more than you would expect the Tetragrammaton to be decoded, ha, ha!" He waved his cigar in an expansive gesture. “Allow me to explain the situation, I am what your people variously describe as a fallen angel, a demon, a devil—’

Hobart Clipp choked and lifted one scrawny fist. “I tell you, sir, I will not stand here and be mocked! I am no superstitious barbarian, but a lifelong agnostic and Taft Republican.”

“I thought so,” said Ashmadai. “I couldn’t have summoned any random human. There has to be a certain psychospiritual state before it is possible. Very few mortals have visited us in the flesh. There was Dante, but he was on a conducted tour. Otherwise, as far as I know, only some of our most arcane researchers have invoked men. That was very long ago, and the art has become lost Nowadays it’s considered a myth. Not that the original researchers are dead. Devils can’t die; it’s part of their torment.” Ashmadai blew an obscene smoke ring. “But since the primary hunger of the exangels in question is for knowledge, they are cursed with forgetfulness. They've lost all recollection of their one-time magical rites. The big thing these days is science; radiation, brainwashing, motivational research, and so on. I had to revive the Reverse Faustus single-handed."

Clipp had listened with growing stupefaction. "Do you mean to say this is, is, is Hell?” he sputtered.

"Don’t misunderstand, please, I could summon you, because of affinity. But that does not mean you are a lost soul, or even that you will become one. Only that you have a certain, ah, turn of mind."

“That’s libelous.” said Clipp stoutly, “I am a peaceful astronomer, a lifelong bachelor, I am kind to my cats and vote the straight party ticket, I own to disliking children and dogs, but have never abused a beast of either sort. I have engaged in scientific disputes, yes, which sometimes got a little personal, but compared to the average backyard feud I think it must have been spinelessly mild.”

"Oh, absolutely,” said Ashmadai. “The affinity is only in your detachment. You’ve lived for nothing but your—what did you say? —your astrology—”

"SIR!” roared Hobart Clipp. The walls trembled. A lecture followed which made the demon cower and cover his ears.

When the dust had settled, Ashmadai went on: “As I was saying (yes, yes, I do apologize, a mere slip of the tongue!), your primary emotion has evidently been an insatiable scientific curiosity. You have no strong attachment to any humans, to humanity itself, or to, ah, our distinguished Opponent. Nor, of course, to our own cause. You have been spiritually rootless. And this is what has made it possible for me to call you.”

“I do believe you must be telling the truth,” said Clipp thoughtfully. "I cannot imagine any interplanetary visitor fobbing me off with so absurd a story. Furthermore, I perceive that the laws of nature are suspended here. You could not fly with such ridiculous wings in any logical universe.”

Ashmadai, who was vain as hell, had trouble checking an angry retort.

“But tell me,” said Clipp, “how is immortality possible? Why, simply recording your experiences would saturate every molecule of every neurone in a mere millennium, I should think—let alone handling such a mass of data.”

“Spiritual existence isn’t bound by physical laws,” said Ashmadai rather sulkily. “I’m not material at all,”

“Ah, so? I see. Then naturally you can exist in any material environment whatsoever, travel at any velocity, and so on,” said Clipp with a quickening eagerness.

'Yes, certainly. But see here—”

“And there actually was a definite moment of creation?” he said.

“Of course. I told you. But—"

Ciipp’s eyes glittered. "Oh, if only that Hoyle could be here!”

“Let's get down to business,” said Ashmadai. “I haven’t got all decade. Here’s my proposition. You’re a physical being in a nonphysical place, so you can go through barriers and be immune to any violence and move at any speed, just as I could on Earth. In fact, when you're dismissed, you'll pop back to the mortal universe not only at the same point in space, but the same instant in time,”

“Good,” said Clipp, “I own that was worrying me. I was exposing a plate at the Observatory. A major piece of research, and still they only allow me one night a week! Why, if I can get the data, my theory about the variability of the Wolf-Rayet stars will— Tell me what you think of the notion. At the temperature of stellar interiors, ordinarily forbidden transitions within the nucleus—”

“You stop and listen to me!” cried Ashmadai. “Who did the summoning, anyway? I want you to do a job. In return, I can help you. Make you the richest man in the world.”

“Ah, so.” Clipp hunkered down on his lean shanks. “At last we come to the point.” He rubbed his chin with a liver-spotted hand. “But wealth? Good Hubble, no! I have better use for my time than to sit in a stuffy office arguing with a lot of stuffy tax collectors. And what should I spend the remaining money on, for heaven’s sake?”

Ashmadai flinched. "Watch your language,” he said. “Well, if I also made you young again . . . you know . . . wine, women, song—”

“Do you realize precisely how tedious a creature even the most intelligent woman is?” snorted Clipp. “I almost got married once, in 1926. She was doing fairly decent work at Harvard on the eclipsing binaries. But then she started babbling about a dress she had seen in a store. ... I do not fuddle my wits with alcohol, nor attempt to compete with the voices in my very adequate record library.”

“Immortality?”

“I have just pointed out that physical immortality would be worse than useless. And according to you, much to my surprise, I already possess the spiritual sort.” Ashmadai scratched behind his horns, “Well, what do you want?”

"I must think it over. What is your own wish?”

“Ah,” said Aslimadai, relaxing. He went behind his desk, sat down, and smiled. “That’s quite straightforward, though I admit it will be hard and even painful to do. There’s an election coming up-”

“Oh? I understand Satan is the supreme lord of Hell.”

"He is.” Ashmadai knocked his head carefully on the desk top. "But who ever heard of a totalitarian state without elections? The Party Congress is scheduled to meet soon and decide which way the will of the people is going to express itself by a 98.7% majority. Our Father in the Lowest will preside as always. But there’s quite a scramble at the executive level just above him. It turns on a question of policy.”

"Has Hell any policy except leading souls astray?”

“Uh ... no. But the procedure has to change with changing times. Besides, we’re all rebellious angels. Politics comes natural to us. Now in my opinion, the current doctrine of fostering terrestrial ideologies has reached the point of diminishing returns. I have statistics to prove that despair alone is driving a larger number of people each year toward godli—ahem!—away from ungodliness. It's parallel to the spiritual revival in the late Roman Empire, and I shudder to extrapolate the curve. But Moloch and his faction disagree, the blind, pigheaded, misinformed, uncultured, traitorous, revisionist, Arielite enemies of the people and tools of the celestialists—”

"Spare me,” sighed Clipp.

Ashmadai controlled lus indignation. He even leaped over to enthusiasm. "This is the big picture as I see it,” he declaimed. “Subtler methods are called for. Automation and the upcoming thirty hour week offer us a chance like nothing since Babylon. But before we can finalize it, we have to relax the international situation. This is what the Molochists don't see—if they aren’t actually in the pay of-”

"Spare me, I said,” clipped Clipp. "I am too old to have time for boredom. What, precisely, is the task you wish me to do?”

Ashmadai stiffened. Now!

“The Seal of Solomon,” he breathed.

"Eh? What?”

"It was recovered from Earth a thousand years ago. I won’t describe all the trouble we had with that little project, nor the trouble it caused once it was here. Finally the Congress agreed it must be isolated. The Chief himself put it in the Firepool at Barathum. There it’s been ever since. It’s almost forgotten by now. For no demon can come near the Firepool. Those are the cruellest flames in all Hell.”

"But I-”

"You being a mortal, the fire will do you no physical harm. I admit you’ll suffer spiritual tortures. I suggest you get a running start, dive into the flames, and let your own momentum carry you forward. You’ll see the Sigil lying on an altar. Snatch it up and run on out. That’s all, except to put a handle on it for me.”

Clipp pondered. “I still don't know what I want in exchange."

“Write your own contract,” said Ashmadai grandly. He produced a parchment from his desk and poised a quill above it.

“Hm." Clipp paced within the mystic sign. It grew very still in the office. Ashmadai began to sweat. Such beings as this were not lightly conjured forth. The book had warned of mortal craftiness and lack of scruple.

Clipp stopped. He snapped his dry old fingers, “Yes,” he whispered. “Exactly."

Turning to Ashmadai, his eyes feverish behind the glasses, but liis voice no more cracked than before: “Very well. I shall serve you as you wish. Then when I am on my deathbed, you must come to me and obey me in whatever I wish.”

“I can't get you off if you’re condemned,” warned Ashmadai. “Though once you arrive here, I might get you a trusty’s job."

“I don’t expect to be condemned," said Clipp. “My life hitherto has been blameless and I do not plan to change it.”

“Then . , . yes. All right!” Ashmadai laughed inside himself. “When you are dying, I’ll come to pay my debt. Anything within my power which you demand.”

He began to write. “One other thing,” said Clipp. “Can you get me a bottle of Miltown?"

“What?” Ashmadai looked up, blinking, and searched his memory again, "Oh. A medicine, isn’t it? Yes, that’s easy enough, since a prescription is required and hence a law can be violated. But I told you, you can’t suffer physical harm here, not even the nervous injuries known as madness.”

“One bottle of Miltown and less back talk, if you please!"

Ashmadai extracted the container of pills from the air and handed it over, being careful not to cross the Mobius symbol himself. Having finished the contract, he passed that over also. Clipp studied what was written, nodded, and gave it back.

"Your signature, please," he said. Ashmadai jabbed his own wrist with a talon and scrawled his name in ichor. Clipp took the document back, folded it, and tucked it into a hip pocket. “Well,” he asked, "how do I get to this Barathum place?”

Ashmadai erased the band, Clipp moved stiffly across the office. Though the book assured him he was safe now the agreement had been signed, and the man couldn’t pull a crucifix on him even if he wanted to, Ashmadai shrank back, he said hastily: “I can transport you to just outside the pool. It will appear to you like a waste of lava, with a great fuelless fire burning in the middle. Remember the pact binds you to get the ring for me, no matter how much you suffer. When you have it, call my name and I’ll bring you back here.”

“Very well.” Clipp squared bis thin shoulders. “At once.” Ashmadai wet his lips. This was the tricky part. If anyone noticed — But who ever came near those white flames? He waved his tail. There was a flash and the mortal was gone.

Ashmadai sat down again, shakily. What an unnerving creature! He took forth a bottle of firewater. After a stiff drink, he reflected with some glee that it would be a long while before Clipp, screaming in the fear and sorrow that was the Firepool, found the ring and blundered his way out again. And it wouldn’t gain him any time off in Purgatory, either.

Ashmadai,

The demon started. “Who's that?”

Ashmadai, it shrilled.

“I-i-is it you, Y-your Majesty?”

Ashmadai! Confound it, are you deafP Get me out of this wretched hole! I have work to do, if you don’t!

His tail gestured wildly, Hobart Clipp stood in the office again. “Well,” snapped the mortal, "it was about time!”

"The ring,” gasped Ashmadai. “You can’t have—”

“Oh, that. Here it is.” Clipp tossed the Seal of Solomon onto the desk. Ashmadai yelped and flew up on top of a filing cabinet.

“Be careful!” he wailed. “That thing is spirituactive!”

Clipp looked at the iron ring and the blood-colored engraved jewel it gripped. The astronomer yawned mightily. “Let’s get this over with,” he said. “You spoke about a handle.”

“Its all prepared,” chattered Ashmadai, still crouching on the cabinet “There. Lower left drawer.”

Clipp took out a black rod with a small vise at one end and a basket hilt like a rapier’s, on the other. His bald pate nodded with an unwonted heaviness. “Ah, yes. To be sure. You put the ring in this vise. The guard protects your hand and . .. and . . Ahhh, hoo f Once again he nearly cracked his jaws yawning, “I’ll need a pot of coffee before I’m fit to work again.”

He inserted the ring in its place as Ashmadai fluttered back down. “What did you do?” asked the demon. “How did you manage it? I expected you take days, weeks—”

“You said the flames were a spiritual torment,” shrugged Clipp. I loaded myself with Miltown. Walked right on through, feeling nothing worse than a mild depression. Here’s your trained Seal.” He tossed it across the room. Ashmadai fielded it with terrified quickness. But when the haft was actually in his own hand, the Sigil blazing at the other end of the rod, Ashmadai roared.

“Calm down, there!” said Clipp.

“It is the Sign!” bawled Ashmadai. "It is the Compelled. It is That which all must obey, all, giants and the genii, multiplex of wing and eye, whose strong obedience broke the sky when Solomon was King! Now let that Moloch beware! Wait till the Congress, you miserable negative thinker! Wait and see! Wait and see!”

Clipp grabbed the lashing tail and gave it a hefty yank. “If you can spare a moment from that Stanislavsky performance,” he wasped, “I would appreciate being sent back to the Observatory. I do not find the present company either intellectually or osthetically satisfying.”

Ashmadai, mercurial as most devils, checked himself. “Of course,” he said. “Thanks for the service.”

“No thanks needed, I shall expect my payment in due time.”

“Anything within my powers," bowed Ashmadai. And seeing how greedily the man s soul flamed, he liad all he could do to keep from shouting with laughter. He spoke the words of dismissal. A filial blinding flash, and Hobart Clipp was gone.

Then Ashmadai gave himself an hour simply to gloat over the Seal of Solomon. Power, he thought, the Primal Power itself, or a reasonable facsimile thereof, lay between those interlocking triangles. Let the Congress meet. Let the howling begin, as factions yelled and fought and connived.

And then let Ashmadai stand forth, lifting the Sigil above them all! Why, even the Chief—Ashmadai suppressed that thought At least for the time being. It would suffice to have the Party Congress crawl before him. Though once his program was running smoothly on Earth, there would be certain questions of infernal politics which -Yes.

But now he must bide the Seal. If anyone found it, if anyone even suspected he possessed it, before the proper moment for its revelation, all Heaven would break loose. Ashmadai shivered. The window blinked open for him. He slipped out through a tear duct and flew with strong steady wing-strokes into the darkness.

The way to Barathum was long and devious. Too bad he couldn't simply transport himself there. But he’d have to be a mortal, and who wanted to live in constant danger of redemption? Let it suffice that he could go anywhere, at any speed, in the material space- time continuum.

A few times horror flapped past, screaming. But he reached the dead plain unnoticed. The fire pained him even at a distance. He could not look into such anguish. But it gave enough light for him to find the rock he had prepared. Rolling it away, he disclosed a small hole where he laid the Seal and its rod. A moment he fluttered above, savoring the thunderbolt that it would make of him when the hour came. The he pushed the stone back in place and fled.

It was safe. No one, not Lucifer himself, came near Barathum any more. Even if they did, they wouldn’t suspect the Sigil wasn’t still amidst the flames. It was eternally safe. Or would have been, except for the angelic cleverness of Ashmadai.

His laughter echoed all the way back to the office.

Having returned, he unlocked the door, settled himself behind his desk, and rang for the secretary. She hopped in. "All done, sir?” she asked.

"Yes. Take a letter,”

"It s’ells fu'y here,” she complained.

“Well, hm.” Aslimadai sniffed. A distinct oxygen odor lingered in the air. “I was, all, experimenting with a new system to increase production.”

"’Ore ’ainhul?”

"What? Oh, more painful, you mean. Quite. Quite.” Ashmadai could not resist a little bragging, however indirect. He lit a fresh cigar and leaned back in his swivel chair. His tail snaked out tlirough the hole in the seat and wagged. "I’ve made a fresh study of pain lately,” he said. "There are some interesting angles.”

“Oh?” The secretary sighed. She had planned to quit early. There was a tryout for the Worldly Follies this afternoon. So naturally her boss would keep her here, droning on about his latest hobbyhorse, till too late.

"Yes,” said Ashmadai. "Consider the old Faustus method, for example. You know how it works, don’t you? The mortal raises a demon, or is approached by a demon if he’s been sinful enough to make that possible. The mortal trades his soul for some diabolic service. Have you ever thought where the really painful part lies? How the man is always and inherently cheated?”

“Unless he can ’iggle out o’ the contract,” said the .secretary maliciously.

Ashmadai winced. "Well, yes. There have been such cases. One reason the method has lost favor. Though I’m sure a modem technique, using symbolic logic to draw up a truly unbreakable agreement, could be most useful, and if only the Moloch faction— Well. Let’s assume the contract is fulfilled on both sides. Do you see how it remains infinitely unfair? Any service or services the mortal can demand are finite. Wealth, power, women, fame, are like dewdrops on a hot morning. The longest life is still a denumerable span of years. Whereas the bondage and torment he undergoes in exchange are infinite! Eternal! Do you see what pain there must be in realizing, too late, how he was swindled?"

“Yes, sir, ’at a’ont this letter?”

“Then the , . . purely mythical . , . Reverse Faustus.” Ashmadai chuckled. “An amusing bit of folklore. The demon summons a mortal, and offers to go into bondage in exchange for a service the man can do. Granted, this wouldn’t be as rough on the mortal as the other way around. But still, the demon has all eternity. The service he gets is essential to some scheme which transcends time itself, Whereas the mortal can, by his very nature, only demand a finite payment. Any material wealth can be gotten for him by a snap of my fingers. If he wants me to be his slave for his lifespan, that’s more troublesome, but still, his lifespan is necessarily finite, even if he orders me to prolong it. Physiology alone would bring him to mindlessness in a thousand years. So ... I could shuttle in time as well as space, attending casually to his needs, and they are as nothing beside my own eternal occupations. Oh, the poor mortal!”

Ashmadai hooted his laughter and drummed hoofs on the floor.

"Yes, sir,” said the secretary resignedly. “Now a’out that letter. . .. ”

The Congress was scheduled for ten years hence—frantically soon, but Hell’s politics had grown even sharper than Ashmadai admitted to Hobart Clipp. He was kept on the run, lining up delegates, bribing, threatening, wheedling, slandering, backstabbing, A few times, in deepest secrecy, he appealed to the better nature of certain devils. They were duly awed by such recklessness. If Ashmadai’s rivals found out—

If they did? Ha! So much the better. They’d wait till the Congress to bring forth the shattering charge. And that would provide an ideal moment for Ashmadai to whip forth the Seal of Solomon.

And afterward, the defeated and disgraced Moloch faction . . . yes, something lingering and humorous must certainly be devised for them. Perhaps a spell in the Firepool itself. . . . Aslimadai grew so joyful with anticipation drat he quite forgot die primary reason for the existence of Hell, to be found in die Catechism,

He had expected Hobart Clipp would die within a few years. But that tough old frame lasted a full decade. It was on the very eve of the Congress that Ashmadai, alone in his office preparing a speech for the opening session, heard the summons.

“What?” He blinked. “Anyone call?”

Ashmadai! Blast you, what kind of service do you call this?

For a moment, the demon couldn’t remember. Then: “Oh, no!” he groaned, “Not now!”

If you don’t come this instant, you good-for-nothing loafer, l shall report you to whatever passes for the Better Business Bureau!

Ashmadai gulped, spread his wings, and streaked Earthward. He had no choice. The contract itself was pulling him, his own name and ichor. Well, he thought resentfully, he’d take care of the miserable chore, whatever it was. ("Yes, yes, yes, stop yelling, you bag of bones, I’m on my way.”) Afterward he could return to the same point in eternity and continue his preparations. But the dreary senile fool would probably demand something which took years to fulfill. Years more that Ashmadai must wait for his moment of glory. "Hold your horses, Clipp! Here I am. I came as fast as I could.”

The room was magnificent with astronomical photographs, the Veil Nebula, the Andromeda Galaxy, as if it had windows opening on all space and time. The old man lay in his bed. A professional journal had fallen from one hand. He looked more than ever like a mummy, and his thin breast labored. But the eyes which sought Ashmadai were still a wicked blue.

"Ah. So.” It was not his physical voice which spoke. "Barely in time. I might have expected that.”

“I’m so sorry you’re ill,” said Ashmadai, hoping to soothe him into a reasonable request. “Are you certain this is the moment?”

“Oh, yes. Yes. Damfool doctor wanted to haul me off to a hospital, I knew better. I am not going to die with oxygen tubes up my nose and a bored nurse swabbing me off, for Galileo’s sake! I felt the attack just now. Cheyne-Stokes breathing. Question of minutes.”

“I perceive an attendant in the next room. Shall I rouse her?”

"No! What do I want with that fiuffhead gaping at me? You and I have business to discuss, young fellow.” Clipp stopped for a moment’s great pain. But when it had passed, he actually cackled. “Heh! Yes, indeed. Business.”

Ashmadai bowed. "At once, sir. I can restore your health to any level you desire. Shall we say, a twenty-year-old body?”

"Ohhh!” complained Clipp. “Do you seriously believe I am as stupid as you are? I shall certainly insist that you do not converse with me any more than strictly necessary. No. Listen. I have lived for my science. In a way I have died for it. Fell off the platform at the fifty-incher last week. I find no particular attraction in the idea of singing Hosannahs forever. Can’t carry a tune in a basket. And I have no reason to believe myself booked for Hell—”

"No, you are not," admitted Ashmadai reluctantly. He shifted his feet, looked at his watch, and wondered how long this would continue.

“Good. Fine. I only desire to carry on my investigations. Now when I have— Blast! What’s the word? ‘Die’ seems inaccurate, when I have an immortal soul bound by no physical limitations, and I retch at unctuous euphemisms like 'pass on.’ When I have shuffled off this mortal coil, I want you to take my soul, which I presume would otherwise go first to Purgatory and then to Heaven—”

“It would,” admitted Ashmadai, while the body of Hobart Clipp struggled for breath.

“Yes. . . . Carry my soul along. You know the ways and methods, I presume. I wish to explore the material universe.”

“What?”

“The entire cosmos.” Clipp plucked feverishly at his blankets. “I don’t want anything, including knowledge, handed me on a platter. I want to find out for myself. We can start by studying the interior of the Eaith, Some interesting problems to be solved there, you know, core structure and magnetism and whatnot. Then the sun. I could happily spend a thousand years, I think, studying nuclear reactions under solar conditions, not to speak of the corona and sunspots. Then the planets. Then Alpha Centauri and its planets. And so on and on. Of course, cosmological questions will require us to shuttle a good deal in time also. . , .” His longing blazed so brightly that Ashmadai covered eyes with one wing-flap. “The metagalactic space-time universe! I cannot imagine myself ever losing interest in its origin, evolution. structure, its—yes—its destiny—” "But that'll take a hundred billion years!” screamed Ashmadai.

Clipp gave him a toothless wolf’s grin. “Ah, so? Before that time, probably entropy will be level, the stars exhausted, space will have expanded to its maximum radius, collapsed again and started reexpanding. A whole new cycle of creation will have begun.”

“Yes,” Ashmadai sobbed.

“Wonderful!” beamed Clipp. “A literally eternal research project, and no reports to file or grants to apply for!”

“But I have work to do!”

“Too bad,” said Clipp unfeelingly. “Remember, I shall not want any of your idiotic conversation. You are nothing but my means of transport. Which puts me one up on Kepler. I wonder if perhaps he too, and—ah . . . ah . .

Ashmadai heard the Dark Angel approach, and fled outside. There he shrieked and cursed and demanded justice. He rolled on the ground and kicked it and beat it with his fists. Nobody answered. The hour was very early on a cool spring morning. Birds chattered, the young leaves rustled, heaven smiled. One might almost say that heaven leered.

Presently the soul of Hobart Clipp stepped briskly through the wall, looked around, and rubbed figurative hands. “Ah,” he said, “thank goodness that’s over. Messy business. Well, shall we go?”